<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<eml:eml xmlns:eml="https://eml.ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.2.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:stmml="http://www.xml-cml.org/schema/stmml-1.2" packageId="edi.1497.15" system="EDI" xsi:schemaLocation="https://eml.ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.2.0 https://eml.ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.2.0/eml.xsd">
  <access authSystem="https://pasta.edirepository.org/authentication" order="allowFirst" scope="document">
    <allow>
      <principal>public</principal>
      <permission>read</permission>
    </allow>
    <allow>
      <principal>cvpia</principal>
      <permission>write</permission>
    </allow>
  </access>
  <dataset>
    <shortName>Butte Creek RST</shortName>
    <title>Monitoring juvenile Chinook salmon outmigration using rotary screw traps on Butte Creek</title>
    <creator>
      <individualName>
        <givenName>Grant</givenName>
        <surName>Henley</surName>
      </individualName>
      <organizationName>California Department of Fish and Wildlife</organizationName>
      <electronicMailAddress>grantton.henley@wildlife.ca.gov</electronicMailAddress>
    </creator>
    <associatedParty>
      <individualName>
        <givenName>Anna</givenName>
        <surName>Allison</surName>
      </individualName>
      <organizationName>California Department of Fish and Wildlife</organizationName>
      <electronicMailAddress>anna.allison@wildlife.ca.gov</electronicMailAddress>
      <role>principal investigator</role>
    </associatedParty>
    <pubDate>2025-01-28</pubDate>
    <abstract>
      <para>
    The California Department of Fish and Wildlife (CDFW) conducts
    juvenile salmonid emigration monitoring on Butte Creek at the
    Parrot-Phelan Diversion Dam near Chico, California. Monitoring is
    conducted annually from October through June utilizing an 8-ft
    diameter rotary screw trap (RST) and a diversion screen trap (DST).
    Data from this monitoring is used to estimate juvenile spring-run
    Chinook salmon (Oncorhynchus tshawytscha) abundance and passage,
    identify alevin emergence timing, document juvenile size at
    emigration, and document rearing and emigration patterns. This data
    will also be used to inform the development of a juvenile production
    estimate (JPE) for spring-run Chinook salmon in the Sacramento River
    Watershed as required by Condition of Approval 7.5.2 of Incidental
    Take Permit No. 2081-2019-006-00 (ITP) issued by CDFW to California
    Department of Water Resources (DWR) for the long-term operation of
    the State Water Project. Salmonid data collected from the Butte
    Creek RST, among other datasets, is also used by the Salmon
    Monitoring Team (SaMT) to understand the movement of juvenile salmon
    in the Sacramento River Watershed to estimate the number of
    winter-run and spring-run Chinook salmon that have entered the
    Sacramento-San Joaquin Delta (Delta). SaMT is a real-time operations
    monitoring team required by Condition of Approval 8.1.2 of the ITP
    which meets weekly from October through June, to provide advice for
    real-time management of SWP operations to DWR, CDFW, and the Water
    Operation Management Team (WOMT) to minimize take of winter-run and
    spring-run Chinook salmon in the Delta.
  </para>
      <para>
    Note: data within the current year’s monitoring season are
    considered provisional.
  </para>
    </abstract>
    <keywordSet>
      <keyword>spring run</keyword>
      <keyword>fall run</keyword>
      <keyword>trap</keyword>
      <keyword>catch</keyword>
      <keyword>juvenile production estimate</keyword>
      <keyword>Oncorhynchus tshawytscha</keyword>
      <keyword>RST</keyword>
      <keyword>California</keyword>
      <keyword>Central Valley</keyword>
      <keyword>SRJPE</keyword>
      <keyword>Chinook salmon</keyword>
    </keywordSet>
    <intellectualRights>
      <para>This information is released under the Creative Commons license - Attribution - CC BY (https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/). The consumer of these data ("Data User" herein) is required to cite it appropriately in any publication that results from its use. The Data User should realize that these data may be actively used by others for ongoing research and that coordination may be necessary to prevent duplicate publication. The Data User is urged to contact the authors of these data if any questions about methodology or results occur. Where appropriate, the Data User is encouraged to consider collaboration or co-authorship with the authors. The Data User should realize that misinterpretation of data may occur if used out of context of the original study. While substantial efforts are made to ensure the accuracy of data and associated documentation, complete accuracy of data sets cannot be guaranteed. All data are made available "as is." The Data User should be aware, however, that data are updated periodically and it is the responsibility of the Data User to check for new versions of the data. The data authors and the repository where these data were obtained shall not be liable for damages resulting from any use or misinterpretation of the data. Thank you.</para>
    </intellectualRights>
    <licensed>
      <licenseName>Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International</licenseName>
      <url>https://spdx.org/licenses/CC-BY-4.0.html</url>
      <identifier>CC-BY-4.0</identifier>
    </licensed>
    <coverage>
      <geographicCoverage>
        <geographicDescription>Butte Creek Rotary Screw Trap</geographicDescription>
        <boundingCoordinates>
          <westBoundingCoordinate>-121.7809</westBoundingCoordinate>
          <eastBoundingCoordinate>-121.7141</eastBoundingCoordinate>
          <northBoundingCoordinate>39.7224</northBoundingCoordinate>
          <southBoundingCoordinate>39.6973</southBoundingCoordinate>
        </boundingCoordinates>
      </geographicCoverage>
      <temporalCoverage>
        <rangeOfDates>
          <beginDate>
            <calendarDate>1995-12-01</calendarDate>
          </beginDate>
          <endDate>
            <calendarDate>2024-01-22</calendarDate>
          </endDate>
        </rangeOfDates>
      </temporalCoverage>
    </coverage>
    <maintenance>
      <description>ongoing</description>
      <maintenanceUpdateFrequency>monthly</maintenanceUpdateFrequency>
    </maintenance>
    <contact>
      <individualName>
        <givenName>Grant</givenName>
        <surName>Henley</surName>
      </individualName>
      <organizationName>California Department of Fish and Wildlife</organizationName>
      <electronicMailAddress>grantton.henley@wildlife.ca.gov</electronicMailAddress>
    </contact>
    <methods>
      <methodStep>
        <description>
          <section>
            <title>Trap equipment</title>
            <para>
      The traps used are an 8-foot Rotary Screw Trap (RST) and a
      Diversion Screen Trap (DST).
    </para>
          </section>
          <section>
            <title>Current trap location</title>
            <para>
      The current trap location is at the Parrot-Phelan Diversion Dam on
      Butte Creek near Chico, California.
    </para>
          </section>
          <section>
            <title>Monitoring schedule</title>
            <para>
      Continuously trapping October through June except under high flows
      and unsafe working conditions. Traps are serviced daily within a
      24-hour period, more if needed due to high debris amounts or fish
      catch.
    </para>
          </section>
          <section>
            <title>Daily environmental data</title>
            <para>
      Daily environmental data collected are water temperature (Celsius)
      and flow (cubic feet per second).
    </para>
          </section>
          <section>
            <title>Fish measurements</title>
            <para>
      Fork length measurements are taken to the nearest mm for 50
      randomly selected Chinook salmon and the first 10 Steelhead.
    </para>
          </section>
          <section>
            <title>Fish counts</title>
            <para>
      All fish not measured are plus counted by hand. If juvenile salmon
      are highly abundant, a simple weight count method is used to count
      Chinook in increments of 500-1,000 or more to speed up processing.
    </para>
          </section>
          <section>
            <title>Trap efficiency trials</title>
            <para>
      Natural origin Chinook captured in RST and DST are the source of
      released fish. Trap efficiency trials are conducted once per week
      from December to May across variable flow and environmental
      conditions as catch totals allow. A minimum of three consecutive
      days of fishing after the release date is required for a release
      to be included in analysis. Mortality between the release point
      and the trap is assumed to be negligible. Release site is located
      approximately 1 mile upstream of the trapping site.
    </para>
          </section>
          <section>
            <title>Trap efficiency mark</title>
            <para>
      Fish are marked with Bismarck Brown Y (BBY) whole body stain.
    </para>
          </section>
          <section>
            <title>Note: data within the current year’s monitoring season are
    considered provisional.</title>
            <para>
    </para>
          </section>
        </description>
      </methodStep>
    </methods>
    <project>
      <title>Monitoring juvenile Chinook salmon outmigration using rotary screw traps on Butte Creek</title>
      <personnel>
        <individualName>
          <givenName>Grant</givenName>
          <surName>Henley</surName>
        </individualName>
        <organizationName>California Department of Fish and Wildlife</organizationName>
        <electronicMailAddress>grantton.henley@wildlife.ca.gov</electronicMailAddress>
        <role>Project Lead</role>
      </personnel>
      <award>
        <funderName>California Department of Water Resources</funderName>
        <title>Department of Water Resources Division of Integrated Science and Engineering. Past Funding: U.S. Fish and Wildlife Service Sport Fish Restoration Act Program, Pacific Gas &amp; Electric Company, and California Department of Fish and Wildlife.</title>
      </award>
    </project>
    <otherEntity>
      <entityName>butte.zip</entityName>
      <entityDescription>Zipped folder</entityDescription>
      <physical>
        <objectName>butte.zip</objectName>
        <size unit="bytes">947523</size>
        <authentication method="MD5">8de03052be0a9784a606a7d421ac3d6a</authentication>
        <dataFormat>
          <textFormat>
            <numHeaderLines>1</numHeaderLines>
            <recordDelimiter>\n</recordDelimiter>
            <attributeOrientation>column</attributeOrientation>
            <simpleDelimited>
              <fieldDelimiter>,</fieldDelimiter>
            </simpleDelimited>
          </textFormat>
        </dataFormat>
        <distribution>
          <online>
            <url function="download">https://raw.githubusercontent.com/SRJPE/jpe-butte-edi/main/data/butte.zip</url>
          </online>
        </distribution>
      </physical>
      <entityType>zip</entityType>
    </otherEntity>
  </dataset>
  <additionalMetadata>
    <metadata>
      <unitList>
        <unit id="number of rotations" name="number of rotations" unitType="dimensionless">
          <description>number of rotations</description>
        </unit>
        <unit id="NTU" name="NTU" unitType="dimensionless">
          <description>nephelometric turbidity units, common unit for measuring turbidity</description>
        </unit>
        <unit id="revolutions per minute" name="revolutions per minute" unitType="dimensionless">
          <description>number of revolutions per minute</description>
        </unit>
        <unit id="number of fish" name="number of fish" unitType="dimensionless">
          <description>number of fish counted</description>
        </unit>
        <unit id="days" name="days" unitType="dimensionless">
          <description>number of days</description>
        </unit>
      </unitList>
    </metadata>
  </additionalMetadata>
</eml:eml>
